Guide to the Paul Fishbeck menu collection, 1955-2015
Fishbeck, Paul menu collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Paul Fishbeck menu collection, 1955-2015
8418
Fishbeck, Paul,
.3 cubic feet.
Printed material
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Menus from restaurants with personal reminiscences from Mr. Fishbeck.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Class of 1956, Hotel.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Menus from restaurants in New York, including Fraunces Tavern, Cafe des Artistes, Windows on the World, and Maxwell's Plum (postcards); California, including Aptos Beach Inn; Williamsburg (Va.) including Campbell's Tavern; Illinois: Massachusetts; Vermont; New Orleans - Brennan's; Bretton Woods, New Hamphire - the Mount Washington Hotel and Resort (guest directory) in; Paris, including the Hotel Meurice and Le Drugstore; McClure's in Melbourne, Australia; and the Royal Hawaiian from a Matson ship. Includes personal reminiscences from Mr. Fishbeck.
Menus from a cruise around the British Isles, Ireland, Norway on the SS Nautica taken by John and Helen Babcock.
Additional menus from Louisiana, Australia, Portland (Oregon), and the Restaurant de la Pyramide in Vienne, France.
Additional menus from New Zealand and Australia; also lunch menus from the Dawn Princess cruise ship.
Additional menus from California, Australia, Switzerland, Chicago, and Hong Kong.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Fishbeck, Paul,
Subjects:
Gastronomy.; Dinners and dining.; Restaurants.; Menus -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Menus -- France -- History -- 20th century.
Form and Genre Terms:
Menus.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- The Wayside Inn, South Sudbury, Massachusetts, May 15, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Notes from the collector: I am grateful when places date their stuff. The menu is one sheet about 12 inches by 6 inches and has all the old favorites and I guess was expensive for its day. Salmon was $13.25, filet mignon was $15.75. Something unusual? COOW WOOW – “America’s First Mixed Drink” made with rum - $2.75. Has anyone ever heard of it? They said they made their rolls from flour and meal stone ground at the Wayside Grist Mill, Mass. Meal tax – 5%. Barnie and I and some of our kids stayed overnight in an upstairs room which was quite quiet. That was probably because Henry Ford, after a visit, had the highway moved some half mile away from the Inn. A nice thing to do. Longfellow would have probably done the same if traffic in his day was a problem.
- St. Andrew’s Café at the Catering [sic] Institute of America on the Hudson River at Hyde Park, New York (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Notes from the collector: I image a lot of you have been there over the years. Now the Hotel School does a lot of “joint” training/teaching with the Institute which makes sense. We ate in St. Andrews because we couldn’t get into the upmarket dining rooms or we didn’t have the money or only wore sneakers that day. Smoked tuna steak was $6.50 apple strudel $2.00 and Kona coffee $.75 so perhaps someone can put a date on that menu. I think we were on our way to see my cousin near Ogdensburg, New York, near the Canadian border. Stopped to see Chuck Laforge at Rhinebeck, but he was out of town. Ogdensburg is the home of Frederick Remington, the painter and sculptor of the wild west. If you go to the 21 Club you will see a great deal of his work in the lobby.
- Royal Hawaiian Hotel, main dining room, Honolulu, Hawaii (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Notes from the collector: The pink lady as it is affectionately known. The first time Barnie went to the U.S. was with her mother and they had a break from the ship, the SS MONTEREY in Honolulu. Chateauneuf-Du-Pape 1952 was $3.00. Only French wines on one page. Another with California wines – all $3.00. Prime Rib of Beef at $6.25 included hors d’oeuvres, soup, vegetables, salad (with 1000 island dressing I am pleased to see) dessert cheeses and demi tasse. The menu was not dated, but it was before Statehood as it said a Territorial tax of 3.5% would be included. Matson, the company I worked for at the time, sold their Hawaiian properties to Sheraton for peanuts as I think they needed the cash and to pay my salary. A note at the bottom of the menu says to inform the head waiter if you are expecting a phonecall. How times have changed and not for the better I would suggest.
- Royal Hawaiian, Honolulu, Hawaii (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Notes from the collector: Where my future wife and mother-in-law dined while travelling on a Matson Ship. I am not sure if I mentioned Matson owned the major four properties on Waikiki before selling them to Sheraton.
- Tango, Chicago, Illinois, early 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes from the collector: Of interest is the note on the price of coffee going through the roof. Fifteen times the cost of tea.
- Campbell's Tavern, Williamsburg, Virginia, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes from the collector: Very well done historically with reading material on the back. Every American should go there at least once as it represents the best of America.
- Fraunces Tavern, New York, New York, July 1, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes from the collector: How such a historical place could get into such trouble. Believe they are now closed and looking for someone with expertise and knowhow. The other tavern, Fraunces in New York City is also an icon of Democracy and if in financial difficulty should be bailed out by the government, any government for all to see at its best.
- Hotel Meurice, Paris, France, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes from the collector: Stayed one night as we arrived in town early and our hotel across the road was full. Would have slept in the car if I had known at the time the Gestapo used it as headquarters during the war. A good article on the property in AD years ago. Hotel Meurice in Paris is just around the corner from the Intercontinental which is just around the corner from the Ritz. I believe Ernest Hemingway was the first to enter it after the end of World War II. A man with impeccable taste.
- Cafe des Artistes, New York, New York, mid 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes from the collector: Now closed due to cost burden of employees benefits. Operated by Smazathy, a good friend of the Hotel School. Was privileged to see his extensive library. Probably the best private collection of culinary material in the country and was told he knew the contents of every book. What a shame. Note the menu is rather ordinary for such a wonderful establishment. Shows what is really important - the food, decor and service.
- Woodstock Inn, Woodstock, Vermont, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes from the collector: One of the leading properties in the country. Simple, but adequate menu. Plenty of reading material to pass the time. Note Robert Trent Jones mentioned, went to Cornell.
- Aptos Beach Inn, Aptos, California, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes from the collector: Note to use of stickers to promote "Special Today" But why three? I"ll have the roast beef at $3.85.
- Windows on the World, New York, New York (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Notes from the collector: I can't even comment.
- Matson menu, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Notes from the collector: Note both the Captain and the Chef get a mention. Note the old company has a new owner, The Pacific Far East Line virtually doing the same run. And this menu dates from October on its way from Nuku'alofa to Wellington. A new menu was printed every day by the two printers aboard. Passengers sat at assigned tables each evening for the entre voyage. So if you embarked at San Francisco and returned to San Francisco you had six weeks (42 days) with the same passengers doing the same. And you had the same waitress for the entire trip. That is usually. On one trip I was on a particular one didn't turn up for the evening meal and some passengers asked where she was. The new one said the other one jumped overboard during the night!
- Victoria Station, San Francisco, California (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Notes from the collector: A very successful restaurant chain started and developed by three hotelies which went nationwide before running into problems. The theme was to do with railroads and three or four old freight cars were joined together to make a very attractive layout. The menu is I believe from the original property in San Francisco close to the Embarcadero. I went to another much larger operation in Universal Studios where the company had brought out from England what appeared to be an entire train station/waiting room.
- Trader Vic's, San Francisco, California (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Notes from the collector: An old menu judging by the prices. A classmate Bumps Baldauf was the Manager before he opened his own establishment.
- New York Restaurant, Marseilles, France, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Notes from the collector: Located on the head of the Old Port about fifty feet from the fishmongers with their fresh catch of seafood. The restaurant was primarily a seafood place and actually had one person going around the dining room helping customers open their oysters, crack their crabs, shell their lobster, etc. It was in 1977, we stayed just yards away at a hotel overlooking the port with a view to the unfolding dramas on the sidewalk. The first night a couple of men were seen to be arguing by the cafe in front of the hotel. One picked up a table umbrella and stabbed the other fatally. The police arrived in some sort of van, opened the rear doors and threw the dead man in rather roughly. Who needs television on holiday. My wife had bouillabaisse by the way later in the cafe.
- Tasman Empire Airways Limited, TEAL, menu postcard (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Notes from the collector: Operated in the Pacific from 1940 to 1965 when it became Air New Zealand. The early planes were flying boats made by the English Company Shorts who were the first company to make production aircraft. My wife's father used to fly on these planes from Wellington or Auckland to Sydney and land at Rose Bay. (my wife's maiden name!) The planes only carried some seventeen passengers but in luxury and style.
- MS Ryndam, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Notes from the collector: A main dining room menu on board our voyage to Alaska and back to Vancouver in 1990. You can see the menu is Day 4 so they had a separate menu for each of the seven days. The back page gives a good summary of Holland American Line.
- Huddart Parker Line, MV Wanganella, July 8, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Notes from the collector: On board breakfast is served on Monday, the 8th of July 1957. Note Dolly Varden Cakes - somewhat of an institution. A pretty comprehensive menu on a short trip across the Tasman. This was my wife's first time on a ship, but not the last.
- Caesar's, ca. 1950s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Notes from the collector: The cover page says "Home of the Original Caesar's Salad" If this is correct then this is a treasure. I have no idea where I got this menu nor the date. But it looks like it is from somewhere around the fifties or the sixties. Maybe someone can throw some light on both the origin and the date. The menu is certainly balanced and lively with a wide variety of wines, but none from the northern neighbor.
- Stag's Head and Bear Inn, Coventry, United Kingdom, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Notes from the collector: I combine these two since I got them more or less together on our sojourn to England. They are from around Coventy as one says. A friend and his wife took us to that area where we rented a car to go touring. He used to work in the area in automotive sales, but lamented now there were no major English car manufacturers owned by the English. The year was 1998. And the menus were certainly indicative of the forthcoming season. To digress - we stayed with our friends for a few nights in their quaint village called Ashby St. Ledgers which like most of England is filled with history. The Manor House was apparently the site of the hatching of the Gunpowder Plot in 1605 with Guy Fawkes in attendance. A long time ago the Manor House was a gift to a nobleman from William the Conqueror. The church in the village dates back to the middle ages and open to the public for inspection. A bit unnerving walking down the aisles knowing there were people buried under the stone flooring. Our friends lived there some ten years and the neighbors still called them Mr. and Mrs. Smith. old port
- Brennan's, New Orleans, Louisiana (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Notes from the collector: Breakfast menu and Dinner menu - both very involved and expensive. Probably in the late eighties when we did a grand tour of the U. S. and spent some time staying with a fraternity brother who was born in New Orleans and is the only person I have even known who has always lived at the same address. He organized a "swamp" tour and it felt like we were in the middle of the Amazon until a plane flew over and someone said we were just pass the airport. He took us up the Mississippi River and showed us a bridge spanning the river. He said to look closely and note there were not any approaches to the bridge. A local politician promised a bridge if elected, but said nothing about the approaches. We stopped at Oak Alley on the way and the place is famous for being in plenty of ads due to its magnificent tree lined avenue from the front gate to the house. A commercial was actually being filmed the day we were there so we helped ourselves to ice cold drinks set out for the filming crew. It was very hot!
- The Mount Washington Hotel and Resort Guest Directory, Bretton Woods, New Hampshire (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Notes from the collector: Not a menu as such, but indicates the high level of everything they attempt. Built in 1902 it is the largest timber building in New England. I think I got that right. It was the site of the Bretton Woods Conference in the 1940's where the free world leaders and or finance ministers worked out the monetary system to be adopted after WWII. As the location was so remote I suppose it was selected for security reasons. We read or were told that during the days before cars became popular several passenger trains arrived each and every day bringing trainloads of tourists summer and winter. We stayed across the main highway in one of the properties and had a rail line run behind. Waiting for dinner we took a short walk along the tracks which were still in place and then rolled down the embankment to the highway. At the exact spot we found a plaque almost hidden by bushes which indicated a railroad named something, something, and Ogdensburg. I mentioned another line which had Ogdensburg in its name, being the hometown of my Dad. The other marvel in the area is the Cog Railway which runs to the top of Mt. Washington, the highest peak east of the Mississippi I recall. The highest winds in the U. S. were recorded there in the thirties. The other notable fact is the railway was the first to adopt the technology of using cogs on such mountains. We beat the Swiss by one year!
- Le Drugstore, Paris, France, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Notes from the collector: A fun place in busy area of Paris. The English translations seem to be hidden away for only some items, but it doesn't matter in gay Paree.
- Clyde's, Washington, D.C (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Notes from the collector: No menu, but an early postcard of the first, I think, operation in Georgetown. The company now has say ten or more operations covering D. C. and outer areas. The last time we were there we encountered a bomb scare with a package left on the street. The police told everyone to vacate the restaurant via the rear entrance as the fun was over. I asked the waiter if we still had to pay. Unfortunately he said yes. We became a little nervous in the drama as we were dining with two fraternity brothers and their wives. One was the first U. S. Ambassador to Albania, a country which had just come out of the cover of communism and a very poor country.
- Maxwell's Plum, New York, New York, Mid 1970s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Notes from the collector: The owner had been in the movie industry mainly in design and it could be seen in his designs. I think he also ran the Tavern on the Green in Central Park. Sorry did not obtain a menu.
- McClures, Melbourne, Australia, ca. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Notes from the collector: A family style restaurant on a busy thoroughfare near downtown Melbourne. From memory, the price changes on the menu were handmade and pretty ordinary, but a new government raised wages overnight by some thirty per cent! I talked to the owners years later and he said they lost half a million dollars in their first year of business because they had no idea of how to run a restaurant They made a fortune selling a large wholesale business and decided to open a restaurant. They didn't seek any help so suffered the consequences.
- SS Nautica, ca. 2000s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Notes from the collector: Menus from a recent trip taken by my friends, John and Helen Babcock who live in the next town on the map - Flinders. They have sailed on the SS Nautica around the British Isles, Ireland and a touch of Norway. The smaller menus are from different days noted at the top so you can see where they went. The two larger menus are from the specialized dining areas with meals at no extra cost. I think it is important to mention this as most shipping companies charge something for the specialized dining areas claiming the menu is better, the meals are prepared in a separate galley, etc. etc. Some of these claims are true, some are not. Note on the main dining menu Jacques Pepin has Signature dishes. Most companies have induced a leading chef, be it an American or a Frenchman to do some consulting and add his name to the culinary delights. Usually a male by the way. Their services may include a voyage or two each year to reinforce their activity. A good idea especially if the voyage is a culinary one. The ship is one of the Oceania Cruise Line which bought the Nautica from the Renaissance Cruise Line when it went bust. They had eight almost identical ships taking about 684 passengers. It is easy to identify their origin as such. We went on one several years ago named the SS Pacific Princess and found the size very pleasant. New ships are being launched now which carry around 5000 passengers, Yes, that was five thousand. A veritable city in itself. I recall the Pacific Princess had a main dining room with two sittings for dinner, a bistro/cafeteria for the three meals, a small food area by the pool and maybe one specialty restaurant.
  The new mega ships have almost twenty restaurants/ food area/ places to eat perhaps at an extra cost. So on a seven day voyage you rarely have to eat in the same place twice. On traditional ships there are two sittings for dinner, whereas the more adventurous are offering dinner between say 5 pm and 10 pm which suits more people as they are not tied down to a specific time. I recall on the Pacific Princess one could eat say ten hours per day, whereas newer and larger ships one can virtually eat around the clock. That is if you want to gain fifty pounds in a week! And if the meal areas are closed there is always room service. I know of people who go on cruises for the experience and never get off the ship in port. And nowadays many lines do not require people to dress for so called formal nights. If they do, a reefer jacket or a dark suit will do in most cases. Whereas when I went to sea every night was formal and I mean formal except the first night (unpacking) and the last night (packing). On my first trip or two I had to spend an hour each morning in the baggage room in case passengers wanted to change some item. And the cases were not suitcases, but trunks. And very heavy.
  Note the prices for wines on the main menus. A Napa Valley red for $93 doesn't sound like any bargain which it should be due to being outside most zones for excise taxes. I guess it cuts down on drunken passengers. Also a health warning to cover themselves in case of a problem.
- Various (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Notes from the collector: Lafitte’s Landing – circa 1989. On the Mississippi some 50 miles north of N. O. One of my fraternity brothers is the only person I know who has always lived in the same house except for his university ears. When we were staying with him he suggested this place. A nice short drive, good food and a bit of sightseeing on the way. We stopped at Oak Alley where an automobile commercial was being filmed. We helped ourselves to the refreshing beverages on the porch. Further on, Tim pointed out a fairly new bridge and asked me what I saw which was slightly different. My eyes must have been on vacation too as I couldn’t see anything unusual. Tim said the local candidate for some office promised to get a bridge for the locals across the mighty Mississippi. Tim said have another look and note there are no approaches! The candidate said he would get the bridge, but didn’t say it would have any approaches! Louisiana has always had a fascinating political background going back to Huey P. Long in the early part of last century. Now the restaurant – the chef and owner was selected by President Reagan to go with him to Iceland when he had a meeting with the Russian President!
  The Australian and American Association dinner at the Hilton Hotel sometime in the 80’s. I got to carve the turkey at our table. The detail on American Culinary Heritage is very detailed and thoroughly interesting.
  The Fijian – breakfast menu. Bottom cup of coffee – 25 cents gives one an idea of the date. I was shown the second kitchen currently at that time not in use. Just as well as all the pots hanging up were rusted.
  The Kon-Tiki, Sheraton Portland, 1959. A hotelie, ex fraternity brother Ross Bell ‘57 was the Sales Manager when we were living in Portland. Ross was the head of the Army ROTC Corps at Cornell and thought he would make the Army his career. After being posted to Alaska he soon changed his mind. Tropical themes were very popular back in those days. Maybe the musical South Pacific added to their appeal. Note a daiquiri was 85 cents and a stinger $1. Ross went on to manage the Sheraton Universal and then the Sheraton at the LAX.
  And to top things off one of the best at the time. Restaurant de la Pyramide in Vienne, France between Lyon and Marsailles. The day we stopped there for lunch was the day they were closed, but the next best thing was to get a copy of the menu. Madame Point ran the restaurant after her husband died. Hand written adds a bit of class and a set price was probably way ahead of its time. 150 frances then about $30. Expensive, not when it is one of the great restaurants in the world. The book on Mess. Point is in the Hotel School Library and certainly worth reading. Paul Bocuse was just one of the apprentices who gained from working there. About 1977.
- Kotaraya, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Notes from the collector: Need an hour to read the menu.
- Phamish (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Notes from the collector: Very trendy
- Milanos (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Notes from the collector: A Melbourne institution. on the beach front. They must be confident about their reputation to charge $140 for a lunch.
- Greta Point Cafe, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Notes from the collector: A nautical theme. Note the back of the calling card. The tenth coffee is free. A good marketing idea so customers keep the card rather than throw it away.
- Terroir, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Notes from the collector: An expensive winery restaurant with small portions with large prices. The Dineaid card is a good idea; it only added $2 to the bill.
- Princess Cruises Dawn Princess lunch menus (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Notes from the collector: Coded as the voyage is repeated several times during the summer. Note there is always the hamburger available. Also a profile of the two main players on the ship.
- Maxwell’s Plum in New York City, postcards (Box 1, Folder 8)